Today we'll be talking
about imitation learning.
Great.
So as a partial
recap from last time,
we started talking about
some of the notation
that we use for
representing behavior
and formulating problems as
a decision-making problem.
We talks about states
and observations
where we either have
access to something that
can fairly, completely represent
the state of the world,
or a more partial
representation that we will
refer to as an observation.
We also will be representing
actions or decisions with at,
and then we can think
about a trajectory
as an example of behavior
that we've taken over time.
We also introduced this notion
of a reward function, which is,
how good is a given
state and action.
And lastly, this
notion of a policy
which is either conditioned
on the current state, what
actions do we want to take.
Or conditioned on a
history of observations,
what actions should we take.
And usually this
policy is the behavior
that we're trying to learn.
We briefly mentioned how this
policy can be represented
using a generative model.
And we'll actually touch on
that a little bit more today.
And the last thing
that's not on the slide
is that we talked about how the
goal of reinforcement learning
problems is usually to maximize
the expected sum of rewards.
And today we'll be
talking about one way
to do that by trying to
imitate a good policy.
And in particular,
the plan today
is to go over some of the
basics for imitation learning.
Then we'll talk about
learning expressive policy
distributions, and why that's
important for imitation
learning.
Then we'll talk about learning
from online interventions.
And time permitting,
we'll talk a little bit
about how to collect
demonstrations
in the first place.
So some of the key
learning goals.
This is, in some
ways, orthogonal
to the main topic of the class.
But it's actually very
important to understand in order
to get performant
imitation learning systems.
So we'll be talking about how
to represent distributions
using neural networks rather
than deterministic functions.
We'll also be talking about why
expressive distributions matter
for imitation learning.
And one challenge
that can come up
with imitation learning,
which is compounding errors
and how to address
compounding errors.
Great.
So what is the goal
of imitation learning?
Like the goal of
reinforcement learning,
we want to try to
achieve high reward.
We want to get a good policy
that can do the task well.
And the way that we'll
try to do that is we'll
assume that we're given
some trajectories that
are collected by an expert.
This is our data.
And we'll refer to these
trajectories as demonstrations.
So it's a special trajectory
that is demonstrating
how to perform the task.
And we'll use D to denote
these demonstrations.
A trajectory, it'll be a
sequence of states and actions.
And as an example of what
this demonstration data might
look like, if we wanted to learn
how to autonomously drive a car,
we could have
demonstrations that
are in the form of
people driving cars.
Because people are pretty
good at driving cars,
most of the time,
and so we could
record from the
sensors on a car,
as well as record steering
commands, acceleration,
and so forth.
And using a data set of
human drivers driving,
we could then try to mimic that
in order to train an autonomous
driving agent.
Now, we don't know
exactly how humans drive.
We don't know the
policy that humans
are using in order to drive.
So we can think about
this demonstration
data set as being sampled from
some unknown policy pi expert.
And then the goal is
to learn a policy that
performs at the level or similar
to the level of the expert
policy by mimicking what's
present in the demonstration
data set.
Cool.
So this is the problem setup.
Now, let's think about version 0
of how we could try to do this.
So a very simple way that
we could do this is first,
we're given our
demonstration data set.
So this is some data set that
contains state action pairs.
These are each of
the state actions
and each of the
demonstration trajectories.
And then we could say that
we want to train some policy
to mimic the demonstration.
So we would be
training some policy.
And in particular, we could
think about the actions
that this policy
is going to take.
So if we were to take one of
the states in our demonstrations
and run it through our
policy, then we would get some
predicted action, a hat.
So let's say that this is
sampled from pi theta given
a state in the demonstration.
And then we could
try to basically say
we want this predicted
action to be as close as
possible to the action
that the demonstrator took.
So we could then
minimize the difference
between the predicted action
and the action in the data set.
And we could do
this minimization
over all of the states and
actions in our demonstration
data set.
Once you train a policy such
that the predicted actions are
as close as possible to the
actions in your data set,
then you can just
deploy your policy.
This is a policy that
should be mimicking
the actions in your data set.
This is version 0 of
imitation learning.
So given demonstrations
collected by an expert,
you essentially do
supervised regression
to the expert actions.
If your policy is
a neural network,
this means doing a forward
pass, sample a mini batch.
From here, do a forward
pass on your neural network
to get the predicted
actions, compute the loss,
and then back propagate the
loss into the parameters
of the neural network.
And you do that iteratively
with your favorite optimizer,
some form of stochastic
gradient descent
in order to optimize
your policy.
So it's essentially a form
of supervised learning.
And then from here, you can
then deploy your learned policy.
And it should be able
to mimic the expert
and do something sensible.
So in this case,
we're considering
a deterministic policy.
And we're just essentially
doing L2 regression.
I guess here I wrote it
as a stochastic policy.
But let's correct
that and let's have
this be a deterministic policy.
The expert might not
be deterministic,
and that might lead
to some issues.
So let's actually talk
about that a little bit.
So what could go wrong?
Let's go back to
our driving example.
So we have a data set
from human drivers.
And we recorded the states
or the observations.
We recorded the steering
commands, and any other actions
that we might want to use.
And let's say that for this
particular car, in some cases,
some human drivers might
decide to go straight
and other drivers might
decide to merge left,
maybe because they want
to move to a faster lane.
So our data set might
contain both examples
of going straight in
situations like this,
and examples of merging left
in situations like this.
Now, a question for you.
If you train a policy
with L2 regression
on a data set that
has these examples,
what would a policy that was
trained with L2 regression
do in a situation like this?
So the policy might go to
the middle of the two lane.
And let's see why that is.
In this example, say we
have the steering command.
And if we thought
about the distribution
over actions that are covered
in the data set for drivers that
chose to go straight, their
distribution of actions
would look maybe something
like this, where this
is like 0 steering command.
This is staying straight.
And for the drivers that
chose to merge left,
their distribution over actions
for the steering command
might look something like this.
So this is the
probability of actions.
These are the two examples.
If they're deciding
to merge left,
they maybe have a steering
command of negative 2.
This is if you
stay straight, that
might have a steering
command of 0.
And then in your data set,
the overarching distribution
over actions represented
in the data set
might look something
like this, where
maybe, more likely people are to
go straight than to merge left.
But you get this
multimodal distribution
that has two peaks, one at going
straight and one at merging
left.
And then when you
use L2 regression
to try to fit this data,
what it's going to do
is it's going to
predict the mean.
So it's going to
predict the mean action.
And in this case,
the mean action
would be something like here.
And that would be probably
not very good action
to take because
that might straddle
the lines on the highway.
And also we can see that
this action actually
has very low probability
under the data distribution.
So it's also objectively or
mathematically a poor choice
because it had low probability
under what the data was doing.
So L2 regression is the equation
from the previous slide.
So basically
minimizing this squared
loss between the predicted
action and the true action.
And then the other
question was, what
is the difference between
the green and the red here?
So essentially what I'm
drawing in the green
is this is the distribution
over expert actions.
Maybe I'll use expert
to refer to that,
conditioned on only the data
that chose to go straight.
The blue is the distribution
over expert actions
if they choose to merge left.
And then the red
is the distribution
of actions represented in the
data set for a given state.
The red is actually what
your data looks like.
And this is a gap
here just showing
this is what the
distribution looks
like for one subset of drivers
and the other subset of drivers.
You're asking, can you
sample from the data set
and do what was in the
data set, basically?
Yeah.
So the tricky thing with
sampling from the data set
and doing what's
in the data set is
that, that would look
like a nearest neighbors
approach within the realm
of machine learning.
And it is, in some
ways, a viable approach
to a number of machine
learning problems.
But one big challenge
is that ultimately,
when the car is driving or when
you have some autonomous driving
agent, it's going
to face scenarios
that are different from
what's in the data set.
And when it's in those
different positions,
you won't necessarily have
examples in your data set
that you can just pick from.
So you won't necessarily
be able to say like, oh, I
saw what the expert did
in exactly this situation
because, ultimately, you'll
be evaluating scenarios
that are different.
So what would you do if the
actions are not numerical?
In a slide or two, we'll talk
about discrete actions as well.
So to go over this
example on the slides,
we can say that the data for
staying straight is in yellow.
The data for merging
left is in blue.
The combined data set, maybe
because more people decided
to stay straight, is shown
in the black dotted line.
And then if we train a model
to minimize the L2 error,
then the deterministic
policy will
choose to take an action
that's right here,
which is the mean of the
black distribution, which has
low probability under the data.
Now, you might be wondering,
how often does this actually
happen in practice?
Maybe you might think that this
is a contrived example where
there is variability in
what people would do.
It turns out that this action
actually happens all the time.
People and demonstrators often
do things in different ways,
not just in driving and not
just in key decision states.
And this happens,
especially when
data is collected
by multiple people
because people have
different preferences.
They have underlying ways that
they like about doing things,
and you can't
directly observe all
of those preferences
and all the things
that might affect
their behavior.
And so as a result,
there are some scenarios
where if you have one expert
policy that's always takes
a consistent strategy, it's OK
to use a deterministic policy.
But in many other cases,
it's actually very important
to make sure that you account
for this multimodality
in the data.
And so the natural question
that arises from here
is, instead of just
learning the mean,
could we actually
learn to represent
more of the distribution
of the expert data
and not just the mean?
And so this is where
learning distributions
with neural networks comes in.
Let's start a new whiteboard.
So in the case of the
deterministic policy,
we had some neural network.
I will use a box to
represent a neural network.
And we're taking as
input some state,
and we're outputting
the mean action,
the mean of a distribution.
And so because it's only
representing the mean
it's hardly a
distribution at all.
And instead what we'd
like to be able to do
is have this neural
network actually
output the parameters of a
distribution over action.
And if it can output a
distribution over actions,
then we should be able to
capture more than just the mean.
Cool.
So this is often the way that
we try to learn distributions
with neural networks, is we
actually output the parameters
of those distributions.
So you can think
about it as this.
You have a neural network
outputs parameters.
If the distribution class that
you choose is very expressive,
then you should be able to
get expressive distribution
as output.
Now, let's think about
a couple examples
of what this might look like.
So if your actions
are not continuous
and instead they are
discrete actions,
maybe you're trying
to train a policy
to play a video game
like Super Mario,
then the actions
might be something
like up arrow, down arrow,
press A, press B, right arrow,
something like that.
What the neural
network could output
is basically this categorical
distribution over actions
where, in this
discrete case, it will
output the probability
of the first action,
the probability of
the second action,
the probability of the
third action, and so forth.
And so you can think of this
as a classification problem.
And this distribution is
actually maximally expressive.
And what I mean by that is that
there isn't any distribution
over actions that this cannot
represent because it's a fairly
simple categorical or pretty
simple set of discrete possible
options.
So this is actually really nice.
We can get a really expressive
distribution this way.
Unfortunately, a
lot of the world
is not just one dimensional
discrete action choices.
We often have much
more complex actions,
and that's why we need to think
about how to model distributions
over those actions.
So if we move towards continuous
actions like in a driving
scenario where you
have steering commands,
for example, the most
natural thing to do
is to use a Gaussian
distribution.
We talked about
outputting just the mean
of a Gaussian distribution,
which corresponds to minimizing
the squared error.
But you can also have the neural
network output the variance.
And fortunately, if you
have it output the variance,
it's not going to do anything
particularly helpful.
In this example, it'll just
output a wider variance Gaussian
in order to try to cover
more probability mass.
And it's not very expressive.
And so we want to be able to
use distribution classes that
are more expressive
so that we can
try to ultimately get actions
that are high probability.
So the question was, if we have
some action distribution that
looks like this, for
example, would we be happy
if we can perfectly model this?
Or would that still
lead to issues
where you might have an
indecisive policy that
chooses one mode and then
chooses another mode?
The answer here is that
if you have a good state
representation, then
you should be happy.
And in particular, say you
modeled this perfectly,
and for example,
you chose like this,
and then you start
merging left--
if you know that you've
started to merge left
and your velocity
is moving left,
then the data should
continue moving left.
And so then, at that point,
the distribution over actions
should look something
more like this
once you are in that
state at that point.
So if you have a good
demonstration data
set and a good state
representation,
if you perfectly model
the demonstrations,
you will get a good policy out.
So the question is, is
the only goal in imitation
learning to mimic the expert
or is there some assumption
that the expert was
maximizing some reward?
Generally, if you assume that
what you're trying to imitate
is good, but it
doesn't necessarily
need to be the optimal policy--
and in many real world
practical, messy scenarios,
getting the optimal policy is
like hopeless in some ways.
Generally we assume that you're
trying to mimic something good,
and really the focus is
on trying to imitate that.
So the question is, in this
case, if we do this perfectly,
are we happy with sampling a
mode that is underrepresented?
There are scenarios
where you might
want to try to essentially
do better than the expert.
And maybe in some cases this
mode is actually better,
or maybe in some cases
this mode is really better.
If you want to
outperform the expert,
that's more where
reinforcement learning comes in
and other tools come in.
You can also try to
curate your data set
to try to contain more of the
stuff that you think is better.
But yeah, with
imitation learning,
generally everything that we'll
talk about in this lecture
is trying to meet
expert performance
or meet the demonstrator
performance and not exceed it.
So the question is,
should the parameters
of the distribution over
actions be state dependent?
And yeah, absolutely.
I've been writing this as
the parameters of p of a.
But everything
here is implicitly
dependent on the
state because this
is the output of a
neural network that
was conditioned on the state.
And so in some states, it might
choose to output a distribution
that's really multimodal.
In other cases, it might
choose to output a distribution
that is much more unimodal.
So let's talk about
some more interesting
expressive distributions
with neural networks.
And some of these
will build upon tools
in generative modeling.
And in particular, if we
think about some examples
of generative
models, we won't go
into all the details of these.
But one example of
a generative model
that you might have seen before
is called a diffusion model,
and this is a model that
can output and generate
images of different people,
can be used to generate videos,
and so forth, is very
popular for generative models
over visual data.
And the thing that's really
cool about these image diffusion
models is that they
are able to represent
a very diverse distribution
over images, including
images that are completely
different from one another.
Another example of
a generative model
is an autoregressive model.
You can think about
this as essentially what
happens with language modeling,
where you're predicting one
token or one word at a time.
And this is also a
really powerful model.
And it's much more powerful
than just outputting
the distribution, like the
mean and variance of a Gaussian
and much more powerful
than outputting,
for example, the categorical
distribution over one dimension.
So you can think about these
two as most typically used
to represent either the
probability of an image
given a text description or the
probability of the next word
given the word so far.
And the reason why they're
often used in these contexts
is because these are
very common problems
that people work
on a lot, and also
because they're very well suited
for addressing these problems.
But the underlying technique
behind image diffusion models
and autoregressive models
is extremely general,
and you can use the
same idea to learn
a distribution
over actions given
observations or given state.
So let's talk a
little bit about how
we might use some of these tools
to learn that distribution.
So our goal is to
approximate p of a given s.
One maybe form of
generative model
that's simpler than those
two that we'll start with
is a mixture of Gaussians.
And a mixture of Gaussians is
already a lot more expressive
than just a single
Gaussian, and so it's
a case where we're trying
to model a distribution
as a combination of Gaussians.
And so in this case, instead of
just having the neural network
output mu, we'll have it output
the parameters of a Gaussian
mixture model distribution.
And so in the case
of a GMM, it will
output the mean standard
deviation and weight associated
with one Gaussian, also the mean
standard deviation and weight
of a Gaussian, and so on.
And if you have n
different components,
it will output n
different parameters
for different Gaussians.
So the question is, can
we elaborate more on,
what does it mean for
these distributions
to be more or less expressive?
So essentially, if you have
some underlying distribution,
like how--
let's see.
Maybe I'll actually rephrase
it slightly differently.
So one way to think
about it is it's
essentially the number of
different distributions
you can capture perfectly with
that chosen representation.
And so if you only
use a Gaussian,
then you can only perfectly
model Gaussian distributions.
Whereas if you use
Gaussian mixture model,
you can represent any
individual Gaussian,
but you can also
represent any distribution
that can be
represented perfectly
as a combination of Gaussians.
And so it's strictly more
expressive than using
a single Gaussian.
Now in some cases, it can
be difficult to compare
two different distribution
classes because in some ways
some might be more expressive
or less expressive.
But in the case of
Gaussian mixture models,
it's strictly more
expressive than a Gaussian.
The question is, do you need
to pick the number of Gaussians
ahead of time?
Yes, you do.
You can think about it
as a hyperparameter,
and you could experiment and
look at how well are you fitting
the data with different
numbers of mixture components.
And then there's two other
examples of generative models
that we could use.
The second one is discretized
and autoregressive,
which is just like
language models.
And the third would be to
use something like diffusion
over actions instead of
diffusion over images.
And so we talked a
little bit, just now,
about mixtures of
Gaussians where
we'll be outputting basically
the parameters of a Gaussian
mixture model.
Now let's talk a little
bit about a scenario where
we could try to use an
autoregressive model
like a language model in
order to generate action.
So in this case, there is
a couple scenarios where
you might want to use this.
So you might be in a scenario
where your actions are already
discrete.
And you actually don't need
to discretize in that case.
Or you might be in a scenario
where it's multidimensional,
or you might be in a scenario
where they are actually
continuous and
multi-dimensional,
and then you need to discretize
or tokenize first, and then
use an autoregressive model.
And so if we think about this
back in the driving example,
if we use discretize
plus autoregressive--
let's say that we're
in the driving case,
and we'll just consider
a simplified driving case
where the first action
is the steering angle,
and the second action
is the acceleration.
So if we wanted to represent a
distribution over these actions
using an autoregressive
model, there's two things
that we would want to do.
The first would
be to discretize,
and the second then
would be to formulate
the autoregressive model.
And in particular, when we
use autoregressive models,
it means that we're going
to be essentially predicting
one dimension at a time.
So we first want to
model a distribution
over the first
dimension of the action.
What we would do is, in
the case of steering--
so we have P steering.
Say that we wanted
our prediction
to look something like this.
Now, a Gaussian
can't represent this.
And so we would choose to
discretize it and represent
a discretized distribution.
And what that would
look like is essentially
creating bins for the
different steering angles,
and you would then output
a probability for each bin.
And then something that
looks a little bit closer
to a staircase, these bars would
be the distribution that you're
actually using to approximate
the original distribution.
So for the first
dimension, you would
be outputting each
of the probability
values for each of these
bars, like the height
of each of these bars.
So this gives you a fairly
expressive distribution
over angle.
And then you could
choose to have
a more fine discretization or
a more coarse discretization.
And if it's more fine, you
get more expressivity in terms
of what you can represent.
But you also have to
output more numbers,
so there's a trade-off there.
And then once you output a
distribution over the angle,
then you would want to output a
distribution over acceleration.
And in particular, in
the case of merging
left versus going straight,
if you're merging left,
probably you would be
accelerating more because there
was a car back into the left.
Whereas if you're
going straight,
you're probably more likely to
be keeping your current speed.
And so we want our
distribution over acceleration
to be conditioned on which
steering angle we chose.
So what we'll do is
we'll predict p angle,
and then we will sample a
steering angle from this.
We'll refer to
this for now as at1
because it's the first
dimension of the action.
We'll sample it from
this distribution here.
And then we want to
get a distribution
over the second
dimension conditioned
on the first dimension.
And to do this, we'll then
pass our predicted action
or the sampled action
back into our model
and then have our model
output another distribution.
And in this case, if you
are conditioning on at1
equals maybe an angle that's
negative 2, so something more
left, then you might output a
distribution over acceleration
that has more probability
on higher accelerations,
versus if you condition on a
steering angle that is something
more like 0, then you
might output a distribution
over accelerations
that is smaller.
So the question is, how do you
build your training data when
you are discretizing like this?
Let's see.
So when you build
your training data,
you'll have the
state action pairs,
and you'll be sampling
state action pairs.
And in order to convert it into
something like this, what you'll
do is you'll sample
a state action pair,
then you'll bin the
action according
to your bidding strategy.
And then you'll
apply a loss that
is between the model's
predicted distribution
and the sampled action, which
would be like one of these bins.
And the loss you can actually
just use the cross entropy
loss here.
And so you can think
about it as you're
doing a classification
problem for each dimension
of your actions.
One other diagram that I
think would be helpful here
to think about how we go about
doing this is when you have
a model that's autoregressive,
that's predicting actions,
you often use a sequence model.
And so if you think about
a sequence neural network,
something like a
transformer or something
like that, you would
pass as input your state.
And then you're
predicting a distribution
over the first dimension
of your action.
So this is a distribution
over steering angle.
You would then sample
from this distribution,
and then you'll pass this
sampled action or your chosen
steering command back
into your model, and then
output the distribution
over the next action.
This is exactly how
language models work,
where you'll have
some beginning token.
You'll predict a distribution
over the next word.
You'll sample a word from that,
pass that sampled word back
into the model, and then
predict a distribution
over the next word,
except now we're
doing it over dimensions
of our action sequence
rather than over different
words in a sentence.
Great question.
How do you determine the order
of these different dimensions?
In language models,
it's very natural
because there's a natural
ordering to words in a sentence,
for example, although even
across different languages,
there's some variation there.
It's something that
generally you pick by hand.
You could also, in some ways
treat it as a hyperparameter.
In other cases, there might
also be somewhat natural choices
for the ordering.
So if you're
controlling a robot arm,
for example, you
can go down what's
called the kinematic
chain of a robot arm
where you start with
the base dimension,
and then you go to the next
joint and the next joint,
and so forth.
The good news is
that, in principle,
the expressive power
of this distribution
doesn't change with the order.
Essentially, your goal
is trying to represent
the full joint distribution
over all dimensions.
And the only reason why
you're doing an ordering here
is because, if you tried to
represent a joint distribution
over all the dimensions
at once, there's
a lot of pairwise probabilities
that you would have to predict,
and it's a lot more efficient
to do it one dimension at a time
to represent the full joint.
So the question is, in
the case of a video game,
it was pretty discrete.
Here we're in a more
continuous case.
Whenever we want to use
an autoregressive model,
does that mean we
should be discretizing?
Right?
Cool.
So there's actually two reasons
to be using discretization.
One reason to use
discretization is
it allows you to model a very
multimodal complex distribution.
And so these bars can be
any height that you want.
And so it actually
can model things
that are way more expressive
than a mixture of Gaussians,
up to how fine your
discretization is.
The challenge with
discretization
is that if you have
a lot of bins--
you might have hundreds
bins for one dimension,
and then you're trying to
represent, I don't know,
10 dimensional action
or something like that,
then the dimensionality of
your discretized actions
is going to blow up
if you try to model
that full 10 to the fifth
matrix over probabilities.
And so using an
autoregressive model
helps you deal with
that dimensionality.
You could, in principle, also
use an autoregressive model
with a mixture of
Gaussians, for example,
and that would be
completely fine as well.
It's not like a
common choice per se,
because if you're going to go
through the trouble of using
an autoregressive model,
usually discretization
is a pretty powerful choice.
But yeah, you can also use
it with a Gaussian mixture
model or Gaussians or
something like that.
So the question was around
how we actually train this.
And maybe let's just
walk through how
we go about training this.
So it's actually going to look--
Let's walk through
how we train it.
So we're given some data set.
So we're given some data set
that has state action pairs,
and we're going to want to
train our neural network.
And we're going to
follow a typical way
of training neural
networks which
is to sample an example
from your data set,
or sample a mini
batch of examples.
I'll write it up for a
mini batch size of 1, just
for simplicity, but
you can extend it.
So we're going to be
sampling a state action
pair from our data set.
And once we sample this,
we will essentially
be running a forward
pass through our network
and a backward pass
through our network.
And the key question
that comes up
is doing the forward pass
is fairly straightforward.
And when we do the
forward pass, we'll
be getting some probability over
the actions of each dimension.
And then we need to figure out
what should the objective be.
There's actually
a common objective
that we can think about for
all of these generative models.
And that objective is that we're
outputting these probability
distributions.
We want to be maximizing the
probability of the actions
represented in the data.
Or equivalently,
we'll write this
as minimizing the
log probability of--
I'll write this as pi
theta of a given S,
and this is with
respect to theta.
And so what this
means is we're going
to be evaluating how
likely is the action that
was sampled under our policy.
And then we'll be trying to make
the probability of the action
in the data set as high as
possible, or the negative log
probability as low as possible.
Now, in practice, what
this log probability
looks like is going to be
different for different models.
For a Gaussian mixture
model, what you'll do
is you can write down
the probability density
function for a
Gaussian mixture model,
and then just differentiate with
respect to the mean, variance,
and weight that is outputted
by the neural network.
And for the case of a
autoregressive model,
it's a little bit different.
So what this looks like for
the autoregressive model is
we essentially get
the probability of at1
and the probability of at2
given at1 and so forth.
And this probability,
for this first dimension,
it will just be the
cross-entropy loss
that corresponds to
trying to maximize the log
probability of this value for a
discrete categorical variable.
And for the second
dimension, that's
where things get
a little bit more
complicated because this will
just be the cross-entropy loss.
But you need to figure out which
action you want to use here,
and oftentimes you will use
the action in the data set.
So for the inputs,
you'll often actually
pass as input the state
and the dimensions that
were chosen in the data set.
And then for each of
these probabilities,
you'll be applying
the cross-entropy loss
and backpropagating the
cross-entropy loss back
into the network.
And then at test time,
you'll then actually
be using your own predictions
and passing your own predictions
into the neural network.
But this objective right here is
really the core loss function.
And this corresponds to a
form of cross-entropy loss
for discretized distributions.
And for Gaussian
mixture models, you
write down the PDF
and differentiate.
So the question was, it seems a
little odd to discretize and do
a categorical distribution
over continuous variable,
especially given that a loss
function like cross-entropy
won't take into account the fact
that two bins error is probably
less costly than an error for
two bins that are very far
apart from one another.
This is one downside to
using discretized actions.
In practice, often that
distance is something
that is fairly quick to learn.
And so the outcome is
often still pretty good,
but you might need more data.
And how fine your discretization
is a really important
hyperparameter because
if it's too fine,
then it'll be very
hard to get signal
because if you're off by 1,
you'll get 0 loss function.
There are also other
things that you
can do to try to
smoothen out the data
and smoothen out the labels
so that the label isn't just
like a one hot vector.
You can smooth around
it a little bit.
So that's one
thing that can also
help with that, although it's
a little bit more advanced.
Oh, yeah.
Awesome question.
I didn't actually get to
write the third example.
So when you are outputting the
probability of the third action,
it will be conditioned
on everything so far.
And often the way
that you do that,
is if you're using
a sequence model,
you can then output the
prediction like a sample
from this distribution, so at2,
and then output the probability
of the third action right here.
And if you have a
sequence model that
takes into account
everything from the past,
then it will already condition
on all the actions so far.
So how does backpropagation
handle this when it's discrete?
So only the output is discrete.
And so you can think about it
as a classification problem.
And so if the
weights are discrete,
that's bad for backpropagation.
But when it's only
at the labels,
you're only just computing
the loss function
on those discrete variables,
and then that loss
you can back propagate
in a direct way.
And that's because it's
outputting a probability
and computing a loss
on that probability,
and then you can back propagate
that loss on that probability.
So that outputs
are actually still
continuous values because you're
outputting the height of each
of these bars.
Cool.
So this is a visualization
of this discretized case
where outputting the first
dimension, the second dimension
given the first dimension,
the third dimension given
the first two dimensions of
the action, and so forth.
And this is very scalable.
It allows you to handle fairly
long sequences of actions
similar to language models.
The last thing that I put
up on here is diffusion.
Diffusion is also a very
appealing choice, especially
for continuous actions.
It can model very
complex distributions
over continuous
variables, including
high-dimensional
continuous variables
like images or actions.
And it does so by using
this denoising process
where you start
with complete noise,
and denoise it iteratively to
make it a less and less noisy
version of the action to
ultimately generate, hopefully,
a clean action prediction.
Oh, and one thing that's
notable is just both this model
and diffusion models do
have some iterative process.
In the case of
autoregressive models,
it's iterative over the
dimensions of your prediction.
And in the case
of diffusion, it's
iterative over this
denoising process.
Now, one question I
have for all of you.
So we've talked about these more
expressive distribution classes,
and none of what we talked about
has actually really changed
the architecture of the model.
And I'm curious.
One very important
question is, instead
of having these more
complex distributions,
we could just still use the L2
error, the L2 norm as the loss
function, but just make
the neural network bigger.
And bigger neural networks
are generally more expressive
than smaller neural networks.
So does anyone have thoughts on
how what we talked about here
is different from just making
the model bigger with the L2
loss?
So in the driving
example, even if you
make the network
really, really large,
it's still going to
output just the mean.
It might output the mean
very, very accurately,
but it doesn't actually
change its ability
to represent a more
complex distribution.
And so the expressive power
of a distribution that you're
trying to represent is
actually, in many ways,
separate from the expressive
power of the function itself.
And if you think
about this picture,
again, where you have
a neural network that's
outputting parameters
of a distribution,
there's the expressive
part of this function
of how many functions
can you represent
that go from S to parameters.
And then there's the expressive
power of this top part that,
how many different distributions
can those parameters even
represent in the first place?
And this is a really
important point
where neural
network expressivity
is often distinct from
distribution expressivity.
The expressivity of
the distributions
that it can
represent is captured
by what distribution you're
allowing it to represent.
And if it only outputs
the mean and variance,
it can very expressively
represent functions
that go from state
to mean and variance,
but it can't represent anything
more complex than a Gaussian.
So we walk through this a bit.
So we are given
some demonstrations.
We're trying to train a
generative model over actions.
And this is trying to
minimize the negative log
likelihood of the
expert's actions
given the states and
the demonstration.
And so this equation looks,
I mean, maybe a little
bit complicated, but the log
pi is the log probability
under the policy.
The blue part is
the demo actions
that are sampled from the
demonstration data set.
And this probability
is under the policy
that we're trying to learn.
And then once we
fit this, we should
have a policy that's better
at actually matching what
the expert is doing,
and as a result,
it should be better at
performing the task.
So now why do we learn all this?
How well does the
generative model
work compared to just
using an L2 loss?
There's a couple
of works that have
evaluated this more explicitly.
So here's a transport
task where you
need to have one robot transport
a tool to another robot.
And the policy is controlling
both of these robots.
And we'll be comparing diffusion
and a Gaussian mixture model.
Diffusion is a lot
more expressive
than what you can even represent
with a Gaussian mixture model.
And we'll be looking at two
different demonstration data
sets.
One was a data set that was
just collected by one person,
and then the other
one is a data set
that was collected
by multiple people.
And we'll look at success rate.
And we use diffusion.
We see that, on both data sets,
it's able to do pretty well,
although it does degrade with
multiple humans in the data
set, which means that as you add
more diversity in the data set,
performance can go down.
And with the Gaussian
mixture model,
we see that well, first it
does worse than diffusion,
so expressive distributions
is very helpful.
And second it actually
goes down a lot more
for the multi-human
data set, which
means that the expressivity
of the distribution
is especially important for
data sets that have more
different behaviors in them.
We can also see this on a
real task on a real robot.
So this is a task that's
actually pretty difficult,
hanging a shirt on a hanger.
The data set was collected
by lots of different people
because it's actually a
pretty large data set.
And once you scale
up, it's very hard
to have a single person
with one consistent strategy
collect all of your data,
so it has different people
and different strategies.
And it compares using
either diffusion, which
is very expressive,
or an L1 loss, which
is a deterministic policy.
And what we see first, it's not
as successful as the simpler
simulated task.
But here we see again that
having a expressive distribution
is really critical
for being able to do
the task successfully.
And if you just use L1 loss,
the success rate of the policy
drops by nearly 50%.
Is there any
scenario where you'd
want to use a mixture of other
models instead of a Gaussian?
Oftentimes other models might
already be quite expressive.
So not to my knowledge, but
it's completely inconceivable.
Now, if you actually look
at some of the big models
that people have been
developing in robotics,
they build on what we
covered so far in lecture.
And so these are
foundation models trained
on lots of different
demonstration data
sets by companies like NVIDIA,
Figure, Pi, and this open source
vision language model.
Using expressive distributions,
when you have large scale data
sets is a key component
of these models.
And if you look at
some of the big models
that people have been developing
for autonomous driving at Waymo
and Wayve, the first one uses
discretized and autoregressive
prediction, and the second one
also uses discretized actions
with autoregressive prediction.
Great.
So a summary so far of
what we've talked about.
If you have data from one
consistent demonstrator,
you should learn a unimodal
policy distribution.
If you have multimodal data
from multiple demonstrators,
you should learn a distribution.
You need an expressive
generative model
when you have data from
multiple people, very important.
And one other thing
that I'll mention here
is that the algorithm
is fully offline.
And this is getting
into a notion that's
very important in reinforcement
learning more generally,
which is, offline
algorithms are a bit
different from
online algorithms.
So offline algorithms use
only an existing data set,
and they don't use any new
data from what you're learning.
And online means that
you're using new data
from your learned policy.
And this distinction is
important in a couple
of different ways.
Online means that you're going
to have to actually recollect
data as you run the algorithm,
and so this can be expensive.
If your policy might be
under-trained, in some scenarios
it might be unsafe
to run your policy.
If you're in a medical
domain, for example,
you might want to
not want to collect
online data from a policy
that doesn't work fully yet.
Thinking about
offline algorithms
and online algorithms, it's a
key distinction and a key way
to think about
different algorithms.
So for what we've
covered so far,
we don't need any data from
the policy, so this is offline.
We also don't need to
define a reward function.
Last time we talked about
defining reward functions
for some examples, and we talked
about how, in some examples,
it might be hard to write
down the reward function.
So this is pretty nice.
In driving, you don't
have to write down
all of the ways in which
you might want it to drive.
The downside is that you
might need a lot of data
for reliable performance.
You need a lot of
demonstrations,
and that ties into how
we might try to learn
from online interventions.
So the question was--
for the previous
videos that I showed--
imitation learning
seems straightforward,
what is the research in it?
And is it just doing what
we talked about today?
Well, I guess there's a
number of different things
that went into those
different examples.
So I can walk through
maybe a couple examples.
So in the case of the first
demonstration, a lot of things
went into curation
of the data and also
the architecture of the model.
And so those were two things
that were novel about this.
In the case of the NVIDIA
example, a lot of work
went into trying to use data
from simulation, especially
because collecting data on
humanoids is quite challenging,
and trying to figure out how to
leverage that simulation data.
In the case of the
figure example,
there was also some
architectural design choices
that made it helpful, especially
in terms of running models
at very high frequency.
And in the OpenVLA
example, that was also
an example where there was a
lot of architectural choices
in terms of the models.
And so it's not just exactly
what we talked about,
so there is a bit more to it.
But what we talked about
is a huge driving factor
behind these different examples.
And these two, a lot
of that also went
into different co-training
objectives and architectures.
So we've talked a lot
about how to train models
with imitation learning.
And there's one important thing
that we haven't covered yet,
which is what can go wrong
and why imitation learning is
challenging.
So for this, it's helpful to
look at supervised learning.
So in supervised learning,
we have some data.
And it's usually trained from
one data set that stays fixed.
And the inputs to the
model are completely
independent from the predictions
that the model makes.
Now, this all changes
in imitation learning.
So say you have a demonstration
that is in your data set.
And so each of these dots is
like a state and then state
action, something like this.
And now you're trying to
mimic this demonstration.
If you're trying to
mimic it, and then you
roll out your policy, the
starting from this state,
maybe at the beginning
of the trajectory,
it's able to do pretty well.
But at some point it
might make a mistake.
The policy isn't
going to be perfect.
And so if it makes
a mistake, maybe it
ends up over here
a little further
from where the
demonstration covered.
And now from this
state, it's possible
that it actually doesn't have
that much data from where
it ended up after it
made this mistake.
Even if it was a
small mistake, it's
going to be potentially
underrepresented in the data.
And if it's underrepresented,
it's actually even more likely
to make a mistake in the future.
And so if it's more
likely to make a mistake,
it might actually drift away
from the distribution even more.
And at that point, maybe here
it's actually very far away,
and it makes maybe an
even bigger mistake.
So this is often referred
to as compounding errors.
Because they can start
drifting of the distribution
when you make mistakes,
those mistakes
can then compound as you
roll out your policy.
And as a result of this--
and one thing that you see
here is that the distribution
of states--
this pen, sorry.
The distribution of states
that are visited by your policy
is actually different from the
distribution of states that's
visited by the
expert, and this means
that it differs fundamentally
from supervised learning.
So errors can lead away
from the distribution.
Error can then compound.
The states visited
by the expert are
different than the states
visited by the learned policy.
This is referred to
as covariate shift.
So it's a distribution shift.
And that distribution shift
can lead to worse performance.
It also makes it different
from supervised learning.
So this is one of the reasons
why fitting the distribution
really well is very important.
Because if you
don't fit it well,
and you learn only the mean,
for example, then you're
even more likely to have
these compounding errors.
Even if you do fit it well,
you might still make mistakes
and might drift of
the distribution.
So how can we address this?
One solution is just to
collect a ton of data,
train for as long as possible to
fit the data as well as you can,
and hope for the best.
If you have the
capacity to do this,
it's not a terrible solution.
But there's also
some other solutions,
and these solutions are actually
quite popular in practice.
And basically the key
alternative solution
is to try to collect
corrective data.
And so if we're in
this scenario, what
we can try to do is, as the
policy starts to make a mistake,
we could try to say,
OK, if you're here,
the correct action
is to do this.
And this green data can
be very, very helpful
to allow the policy to recover
from mistakes that it made.
So the corrective data
would be, ideally, you
would learn something like this
that tells your policy exactly
how to recover.
And then if you collect
this corrective data,
then you could combine the data
in green with the data in black,
train a policy on
that combined data.
And then if it
makes a mistake, it
should actually have examples
of how to recover and get back
to the distribution
because we're actually
running our policy
and then getting
examples of how to recover
after running our policy.
Does this not overfit the model
and make it less generalizable?
You will need to make sure that
when you collect online data,
you collect it in diverse
scenarios and not just very
narrow scenarios.
If you only collect it in a
very small amount of scenarios,
then these corrections
won't be as diverse
as your original data set.
So the main difference between
the learned policy distribution
and the expert distribution,
it is just how the actions
led to particular states.
I'm using this as
shorthand for the states
visited by the policy.
And when you start to
incorporate these corrections,
you're expanding the
distributions of states
that you have data
for, and you're
making your
distribution of states
seen in your data
set wider to include
both p of s and the states
that your policy might
be likely to visit
if it makes mistakes.
So in terms of what this
looks like as an algorithm,
we will first roll
out our policy.
So this is what's
shown in blue here.
Then we will query an expert
at the states that you visited.
And these actions in green
are the same as the orange
a star on the slide.
And then we will aggregate
the corrective data
with the first
demonstration data set,
and then we'll update the policy
on the aggregated data set.
And this updated
policy, you could
fine tune the policy,
so warm start it,
trained on the original
data set and then update it
with fine tuning.
You could also
train from scratch
if you're concerned
about, I don't know,
some biases or something
like that, oftentimes you
might fine tune.
And then you can actually
repeat this process.
So you can train on
the corrective data,
get a better policy, and
then maybe your policy
actually starts making
you have another policy,
and maybe it makes mistakes
in a different way.
And in that case, you'd
want to then collect
some corrective data
from that second policy
if a new failure mode or
a new mistake emerges.
And so this is a
repetitive process.
This name has a terrible
algorithm because it's not
very descriptive.
But it's called data set
aggregation or DAgger
because you're aggregating data.
It's helpful to know
terminology, but this, I think,
was a bad choice.
And it's a data efficient
way to learn from an expert.
But it can be hard
to query an expert.
And so getting
these green actions
can be a little bit tricky.
So you might have
to actually ask
a person OK, this is what
my car did on the road, what
steering command should it have
done instead in those scenarios?
And so this data actually
can be potentially very
hard to collect.
So how do we get
the correct data?
What this would look like
is you would run your policy
to get this blue trajectory.
And so this trajectory is like
a sequence of S1, a1, S2, a2,
and so forth.
This is not possible
in some scenarios,
but you'd ask a person for this
S, what should the a have been?
And for this S, what
should the a have been?
Now, there are scenarios
where you can't do that,
and where this algorithm is
just not possible to run,
and that leads into
potentially another way
that we might be able to
collect corrective data.
We might not be able to tell
exactly that this is exactly
the steering command
you should have done
because that's very hard to do.
And so what we could do
instead is instead of saying,
for each of these
actions we want
to query what the
expert would have done,
we're actually going
to let the expert take
full control at some point.
And so what this would
look like is something
where you start drifting off.
The expert notices that a
mistake was made, and then takes
full control, for example,
starts driving the car
rather than letting the
policy drive the car.
And then in this
case, you can then
add those partial
demonstrations to your data
set instead of trying to query
the expert on the policy states.
And so here you would start to
roll out the learned policy.
The expert intervenes when
the policy makes a mistake.
The expert provides a partial
demonstration from the state
that the policy visited, so
it would take full control
and then aggregate this
partial demonstrations
with the original data set in
order to then update the policy.
And again, you can
repeat this process
so that you can cover
different potential failure
modes of the policy.
In all of these cases, the
best performance of the policy
is upper bounded by the expert.
The question was, if
we're detecting a mistake,
is that mostly if you've
collided with something
or something else?
This is something
that's subjective and is
up to the demonstrator
in many ways.
Oftentimes you want to
be a bit more proactive.
And before the car
hits something,
you would want to take control.
And so one of the
downsides of this algorithm
is that it can sometimes be
hard to catch mistakes quickly.
Or if the policy decides
to, I don't know,
drastically change the action
and it was unpredictable,
that can be very hard
to proactively prevent.
And you want ideally
this to be in a scenario
where you can predict.
If the policy is starting
to drift into another lane,
re centering it,
that sort of thing.
This is actually
something that companies
do in driving where
they let the policy run.
They have a safety driver.
And then the safety driver
will take full control
if it seems like the policy
either doesn't know what to do,
and it's like stalling, or it's
starting to make a mistake.
Now, We've seen
failure modes of that.
We've seen cases where
safety drivers were not
able to prevent a mistake
that was more major.
And so there's downsides
relying on the demonstrator
to proactively prevent a
huge mistake from happening.
But it is a practical interface
for providing corrections
in a lot of scenarios, and
can help improve performance
significantly.
So the question was,
can you explain again
why if you're correcting
a narrow corrective data,
why that would lead
to overfitting?
So let's take the
driving example.
If your original driving data
was all over the United States,
and then your corrective
driving data was only
on Stanford's campus, then
when you combine the data set,
it might only learn
that corrective behavior
in a more narrow
set of scenarios,
and might also overfit
to the Stanford data,
leading to a policy that is
perhaps less generalizable.
And ideally, when you
collected corrective data,
it would be in a broader set
of scenarios than campus.